<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-08-11T14:53:26-03:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">Chiropractic Treatment for Spondylosis</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/spondylosis/2019/chiropractic-treatment-for-spondylosis" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chiropractic Treatment for Spondylosis" /><published>2019-11-14T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2023-07-19T12:40:25-03:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/spondylosis/2019/chiropractic-treatment-for-spondylosis</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/spondylosis/2019/chiropractic-treatment-for-spondylosis"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Chiropractic Treatment Can Help Ease the Pain of Spondylosis</strong></p>

<p>Aches and pains in your back or neck could be caused by spondylosis, a condition that occurs after years of wear and tear on your spine. Although popping a few pain relievers can decrease your symptoms, the relief is only temporary and can be accompanied by unpleasant side effects. Chiropractic treatment eases your pain naturally and offers longer-lasting relief of symptoms.</p>

<p><strong>Spondylosis Explained</strong></p>

<p>Spondylosis, commonly called arthritis of the spine, occurs due to several age-related changes in your spine. Thirty-three bony vertebrae support your body, making it possible to stand, bend and lift heavy objects. Small fluid-filled discs located between vertebrae absorb shock, cushion the joints and help the spine maintain its structural integrity.</p>

<p>As you age, the discs begin to dehydrate and shrink. As a result, they can’t absorb shock quite as well as they could when you were younger. Your disks begin to gradually change around age 40, although you may not notice any differences for years.</p>

<p>The dehydration process can cause cracks or tears in the outer layer of disks, increasing your risk of herniated disks. Herniations happen when the soft, gel-like center of the disc protrudes and presses on spinal nerves, causing pain.</p>

<p>The space between the vertebrae gradually narrows as the discs flatten due to dehydration. When this occurs, painful bone spurs may form at the ends of vertebrae.</p>

<p>Age-related changes can also wear away the protective cartilage that cushions the ends of the vertebrae and stiffens the ligaments that hold the vertebrae together, resulting in pain and stiffness when you bend and move.</p>

<p><strong>Common Spondylosis Symptoms</strong></p>

<p>It takes many years to notice the effects of spondylosis. You may only experience occasional symptoms in your 40s and 50s. Your back or neck may hurt or feel a little stiff after you spend the day weeding your flower beds or participating in a 5K. These changes can occur even if you’ve been healthy and active all of your life and practice proper lifting techniques.</p>

<p>Your risk of spondylosis increases significantly with age. The Mayo Clinic notes that more than 85 percent of people over age 60 experience spondylosis in their necks.</p>

<p>Severe neck and back pain can occur if your condition worsens. You may notice that it’s difficult to move or walk and may experience weakness or tingling sensations in your arms or legs.</p>

<p><strong>How Your Chiropractor Can Help You</strong></p>

<p>Chiropractic treatment can relieve pain, improve your range of motion and reduce pressure on your spinal nerves due to herniated discs or bone spurs. After performing an examination and conducting a few diagnostic tests, your chiropractor may recommend one or more of these treatments:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Spinal Manipulation:</strong> Your chiropractor uses quick, hands-on pressure or an activator to realign your vertebrae. Manipulations improve range of motion in your neck and back, decrease pain and make it easier to move the muscles in your neck and back. After an adjustment, you’ll notice less pain and stiffness. Spinal manipulation is among the therapies that the American College of Physicians recommends for the treatment of nonradicular low back pain. Nonradicular pain is pain that doesn’t spread to your arms or legs. Spinal Mobilization: Spinal mobilization stretches the spine and decreases tension in the muscles between your vertebrae with slow, gentle movements.</li>
  <li><strong>Flexion-Distraction:</strong> Flexion-distraction is performed on a segmented table. As your chiropractor slowly manipulates your spine, the table moves beneath you, decompressing and stretching your vertebrae. Flexion-distraction improves mobility, decreases pressure on nerves and discs, reduces bulging of disks, and eases pain and stiffness. Massage: Spinal alignment issues can cause painful stiffening in the muscles of your back and neck. Massage relaxes these muscles and improves blood flow to the area, facilitating recovery.</li>
  <li><strong>Traction:</strong> Traction treatments gently pull and decompress your vertebrae, relieving pain and stiffness and decreasing pressure on your nerves. The therapy can be performed manually or with a special device. Other Therapies: Depending on your diagnosis, your chiropractor may also suggest ultrasound therapy, cold and heat therapy, electrical nerve stimulation treatment or trigger point therapy. Don’t let spondylosis pain take over your life. Chiropractic treatment offers a safe, natural way to control your symptoms. Contact us to schedule your appointment.</li>
</ul>

<p> </p>

<p><strong>Sources:</strong></p>

<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/cervical-spondylosis/symptoms-causes/syc-20370787" target="_blank">Mayo Clinic: Cervical Spondylosis</a> </p>

<p><a href="https://www.arthritis.org/living-with-arthritis/treatments/natural/other-therapies/chiropractic-medicine.php" target="_blank">Arthritis Foundation: How Chiropractors Can Help Arthritis Pain </a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.acatoday.org/patients/health-wellness-information/neck-pain-and-chiropractic" target="_blank">American Chiropractic Association: Neck Pain and Chiropractic </a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.acponline.org/acp-newsroom/american-college-of-physicians-issues-guideline-for-treating-nonradicular-low-back-pain" target="_blank">American College of Physicians: American College of Physicians Issues Guideline for Treating Nonradicular Low Back Pain, 2/4/17</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew Robson</name></author><category term="Spondylosis" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Chiropractic Treatment Can Help Ease the Pain of Spondylosis]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Can Meditation Improve Your Health?</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/meditation/2019/can-meditation-improve-your-health" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can Meditation Improve Your Health?" /><published>2019-11-14T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2023-07-19T11:22:46-03:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/meditation/2019/can-meditation-improve-your-health</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/meditation/2019/can-meditation-improve-your-health"><![CDATA[<p><strong>How Meditation Contributes to Overall Health</strong></p>

<p>Meditation offers many benefits for your mental and emotional health. Regular meditation reduces stress and anxiety, improves your mood and decreases symptoms of depression. Adding meditation to your daily schedule may also help you lower your risk of some health conditions and diseases.</p>

<p><strong>Asthma Attacks May Decrease</strong></p>

<p>Strong odors, smoke, and illnesses often trigger asthma flares, but emotions can play a role too. If you’re stressed or upset, you’re more likely to experience asthma symptoms. Meditation can help you calm yourself when you begin to feel worried, stressed or anxious. Practicing meditation every day is a simple way to avoid flare-ups and keep your asthma under control.</p>

<p><strong>Your Blood Pressure May Lower</strong></p>

<p>Your emotions can also be a contributing factor if you have high blood pressure. The more stressed or agitated you become, the more your blood pressure soars. Unfortunately, uncontrolled high blood pressure can increase your risk of heart attack, heart disease, kidney disease, stroke, and other health problems. Meditation, along with a healthy diet, regular exercise, and medication, can help you keep your blood pressure at a safe level.</p>

<p>After reviewing 19 clinical studies on the effects of medication on hypertension, researchers concluded that non-transcendental meditation was a promising treatment option for high blood pressure. Their meta-analysis appeared in the April 2017 issue of the Journal of Hypertension.</p>

<p><strong>Tired of Living with Menopausal Symptoms? Try Meditation</strong></p>

<p>Menopause is referred to as “the change of life” for good reason. The end of your menstrual cycle is just one of the many changes you can expect during this time. Hot flashes, irritability, difficulty sleeping, brittle nails and itchy skin are among the symptoms that can accompany menopause. Meditation may improve your moods, decrease insomnia and reduce the number and intensity of hot flashes.</p>

<p><strong>Meditation May Offer a Solution for Chronic Pain</strong></p>

<p>Chronic pain can be very difficult to treat. Medications wear off quickly, can be addictive, and often have side effects. People who have chronic pain may have decreased levels of body awareness, according to a group of researchers who studied the effects of mindfulness on chronic pain and depression.</p>

<p>Body awareness refers to the ability to understand how the parts of your body function together and how your body occupies the space around you. The research, which appeared in Frontiers in Psychology, demonstrated that mindfulness can improve body awareness. Once awareness improves, pain may decrease.</p>

<p><strong>Meditation May Decrease Inflammation Responsible for Multiple Conditions</strong></p>

<p>It’s hard to overlook a red, inflamed wound, but inflammation isn’t so obvious when it occurs internally. Chronic inflammation may cause or contribute to a variety of diseases and health conditions, including Alzheimer’s disease, diabetes, irritable bowel syndrome, hay fever, cancer, hardening of the arteries, rheumatoid arthritis, and gum disease. A reduction in inflammation just may be one of the most important effects of meditation.</p>

<p><strong>Meditation Offers a Simple Way to Prevent Respiratory Infections</strong></p>

<p>Would you like to avoid colds and the flu? Regular meditation may reduce your risk of developing acute respiratory infections (ARIs), according to research conducted at the University of Wisconsin-Madison. ARIs are colds, flu, and flu-like illnesses.</p>

<p>Participants aged 30 to 69 were divided into three groups during the study. One group practiced mindfulness meditation, another participated in an exercise program, while a third group served as the control group. Throughout the four-year study, 120 people in the exercise group and 134 in the control group had ARIs, but only 112 people in the meditation group suffered from respiratory infections.</p>

<p>Practicing meditation, in addition to receiving chiropractic care, can help improve your mental and physical health. Are you ready to take advantage of the many benefits of meditation? Contact us for more information on how meditation may reduce your risk of some health complications.</p>

<p> </p>

<p><strong>Sources:</strong></p>

<p><a href="https://journals.lww.com/jhypertension/Abstract/2017/04000/Meditation_and_blood_pressure__a_meta_analysis_of.5.aspx">Journal of Hypertension: Meditation and Blood Pressure, 4/17 </a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.med.wisc.edu/news-and-events/2018/july/exercise-meditation-reduce-common-colds-flu/">University of Wisconsin-Madison: Exercise and Meditation Appear to Reduce Common Colds and Flu, 7/3/18</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/meditation/in-depth/meditation/art-20045858">Mayo Clinic: Meditation: A Simple, Fast Way to Reduce Stress</a> </p>

<p><a href="https://nccih.nih.gov/health/tips/meditation">National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health: 8 Things to Know About Meditation for Health</a> </p>

<p><a href="https://scholar.harvard.edu/sara_lazar/publications/effects-mindfulness-based-cognitive-therapy-body-awareness-patients-chronic">Scholar.Harvard: Frontiers in Psychology: Effects of Mindfulness-Based Cognitive Therapy on Body Awareness in Patients with Chronic Pain and Comorbid Depression</a> </p>

<p><a href="https://www.prevention.com/health/a22679621/health-benefits-of-meditation/">Prevention: 7 Science-Backed Health Benefits of Meditation, According to Experts </a></p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew Robson</name></author><category term="Meditation" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How Meditation Contributes to Overall Health]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is Flexion-Distraction Therapy?</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/flexion-distraction%20therapy/2019/flexion-distraction-therapy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Flexion-Distraction Therapy?" /><published>2019-11-14T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2023-07-19T12:40:25-03:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/flexion-distraction%20therapy/2019/flexion-distraction-therapy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/flexion-distraction%20therapy/2019/flexion-distraction-therapy"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-is-flexion-distraction-therapy"><strong>What Is Flexion-Distraction Therapy?</strong></h2>

<p>Flexion-distraction therapy is performed on a segmented table that moves as your chiropractor slowly manipulates your spine. The manipulations, combined with the movements of the table, stretch and decompress your spine, relieving your back, leg, neck, or arm pain.</p>

<p>As your chiropractor performs the gentle manipulations, a section of the treatment table drops or moves, changing the positioning of your body. When your body drops slightly, gravity enhances the effects of treatment and helps realign your spine.</p>

<h2 id="could-flexion-distraction-therapy-help-my-pain"><strong>Could Flexion-Distraction Therapy Help My Pain?</strong></h2>

<p>Most of us experience pain in our muscles and joints occasionally. If we’re lucky, the uncomfortable symptoms subside after just a few days. For some people, pain becomes a chronic condition that lasts months or years.</p>

<p>Although pain medication can be helpful, it often causes nausea, dizziness and other unpleasant side effects that can make it difficult to drive or keep up with your usual workload. Flexion-distraction therapy, a natural, non-surgical technique offered by your chiropractor, provides an effective, alternative pain relief option.</p>

<h2 id="what-are-the-benefits-of-the-flexion-distraction-therapy"><strong>What Are the Benefits of the Flexion-Distraction Therapy?</strong></h2>

<p>Flexion-distraction therapy can:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Reduce pressure on your spinal nerves and discs</li>
  <li>Decrease bulging of herniated discs</li>
  <li>Improve range of motion and mobility</li>
  <li>Help you manage chronic back pain</li>
  <li>Relieve stiffness</li>
  <li>Decrease neck pain and headaches</li>
  <li>Eliminate or delay the need for surgery in some cases</li>
  <li>Promote good disc health</li>
  <li>Relieve pain and numbness in the back, buttocks, arms, and legs</li>
  <li>Improve posture</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>In a study published in The Journal of Physical Therapy Science, researchers examined the effects of flexion-distraction manipulation on patients with lumbar spinal stenosis. The condition occurs when the spinal canal narrows and presses against the nerves that serve the lower back and legs, causing pain, weakness, numbness, and cramping.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Study participants who received flexion-distraction manipulation as part of their therapy experienced a greater reduction of their painful symptoms than those patients whose treatment did not include the technique.</p>

<h2 id="will-flexion-distraction-help-me"><strong>Will Flexion-Distraction Help Me?</strong></h2>

<p>In addition to improving spinal stenosis symptoms, flexion-distraction can also be used to treat many other types of back pain. It may reduce pain and stiffness associated with osteoarthritis and improve spinal movement in patients who have scoliosis.</p>

<h3 id="conditions-that-benefit-from-flexion-distraction">Conditions that benefit from Flexion-Distraction:</h3>
<p>Flexion-distraction therapy can be helpful if you have sacroiliac syndrome, ankylosing spondylitis, sciatica, spondylolisthesis, sprains, and strains. It’s also very effective in treating muscle spasms or low back pain unrelated to a specific condition.</p>

<p>The technique is gentle enough to use after spinal surgery and can be an important part of your recovery treatment plan. If you have osteoporosis or another condition that affects your bones, some treatments may be too risky. Luckily, flexion-distraction is gentle enough that it can be a safe therapy option for people who have brittle bones or are frail.</p>

<p>Flexion-distraction therapy may even be helpful in treating knee pain. In a study published in The Journal of the Canadian Chiropractic Association, patients who had either acute or chronic knee pain received flexion-distraction therapy for two to three weeks. At the end of the treatment period, the mean pain scale score dropped from 7.7 to 1.8. Patients who suffered from chronic knee pain maintained their results by receiving the therapy once every month.</p>

<h2 id="in-summary">In summary</h2>
<p>Are you tired of living in pain? Flexion-distraction therapy may offer the ideal way to relieve your symptoms, whether you’ve been experiencing pain for a few days or weeks, or you have a chronic condition. Call us to schedule your appointment.</p>

<h4 id="sources"><strong>Sources:</strong></h4>

<p><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/29480409 ">NCBI: European Spine Journal: The Global Spine Care Initiative, 9/27/18
 </a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4500015/"> NCBI: Journal of Physical Therapy Science: Effects of Flexion-Distraction Manipulation Therapy on Pain and Disability in Patients with Lumbar Spinal Stenosis, 6/30/15</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.chiroeco.com/chiropractic-flexion-distraction-tables/"> Chiropractic Economics: The Extensive Benefits of a Chiropractic Flexion Table, 9/15/16</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5596966/">NCBI The Journal of the Canadian Chiropractic Association: Innovative Application of Cox Flexion Distraction Decompression to the Knee: A Retrospective Case Series
 </a></p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew Robson</name></author><category term="Flexion-Distraction Therapy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What Is Flexion-Distraction Therapy?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Does Collagen Help With Joint Pain?</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/pain/2019/does-collagen-help-with-joint-pain" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Does Collagen Help With Joint Pain?" /><published>2019-11-14T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2023-07-19T11:22:46-03:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/pain/2019/does-collagen-help-with-joint-pain</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/pain/2019/does-collagen-help-with-joint-pain"><![CDATA[<p><strong>The Benefits of Using Collagen For Your Joints</strong></p>

<p>Painful joints complicate even the simplest activities. Walking up a flight of stairs, bending or even rising from a seated position is much more difficult when your joints become stiff and painful. Collagen supplements promise to ease your pain naturally, but do they work?</p>

<p><strong>What is Collagen?</strong></p>

<p>Collagen is a natural protein produced by your body. It’s essential for:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Healthy Skin:</strong> Collagen keeps your skin taut and supple. As collagen production decreases as you grow older, sagging and wrinkles occur, and the skin becomes dryer and thinner.</li>
  <li><strong>Joint Function:</strong> High amounts of collagen are found in the cartilage at the ends of bones. Cartilage is the flexible tissue that absorbs shock and helps the bones in a joint glide together easily. Joint pain often occurs when cartilage decreases due to wear and tear or injuries.</li>
  <li><strong>Muscle and Tendon Health:</strong> Reduced collagen production due to aging can also affect muscle strength and mass and loosen the tendons that connect muscles to bones in your joints. Your muscles help support your joints and are essential for normal joint function. Muscle weakness can be a contributing factor in joint pain.</li>
  <li><strong>Strong Bones and Teeth:</strong> Collagen is also found in bones and is responsible for keeping your bones strong. As collagen production declines, you may be more likely to break your bones, even if you only experience a minor fall. Declining collagen production can also cause your teeth to become brittle and break easily.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>What Are Collagen Supplements?</strong></p>

<p>Collagen supplements are intended to replenish your body’s natural supply of the protein. Available in pill, powder, gummy or liquid form, the supplements are readily available in grocery stores, pharmacies, and from online stores. Type I and III collagen supplements are recommended if you want to improve the condition of your skin, while Type II collagen supplements are used for joint pain.</p>

<p><strong>Can Collagen Supplements Ease Joint Pain?</strong></p>

<p>Supplements can be helpful but not everyone notices a difference in joint pain after taking them. If your joint pain is due to osteoarthritis, the supplements are worth trying. They may help tighten the muscles and tendons that hold your joints together, improve muscle mass and rebuild cartilage.</p>

<p>In an article review published in the Journal of Arthritis, researchers evaluated clinical evidence and studies that explored the effectiveness of collagen supplements. They noted that collagen may be helpful in treating osteoarthritis joint pain, although more research is needed.</p>

<p>Other studies considered the effectiveness of bioactive collagen peptides (BCP) in treating joint pain in both athletes and non-athletes. After taking BCP daily for knee pain, athletes reported a 37.5 percent decrease in pain.</p>

<p>The non-athletes experienced similar results after taking the peptides for 12 weeks for hip and knee pain. Activity-related pain improved by 38 percent, while at rest pain improved by 39 percent.</p>

<p>Bone strength may also be improved by collagen supplements. Taking collagen regularly can help you avoid painful fractures by increasing the density and strength of your bones.</p>

<p>Collagen supplementation, coupled with chiropractic treatment, offers a natural way to treat joint pain. Your chiropractor can correct misalignments and muscle imbalances that cause or worsen joint pain. Treatments also reduce stress on your joints, promote healing, ease stiffness, and improve range of motion.</p>

<p>Are your joints stiff and achy? Chiropractic care can help you reduce your painful symptoms. Contact our office to schedule an appointment.</p>

<p> </p>

<p><strong>Sources:</strong></p>

<p>Arthritis Foundation: Are Collagen Supplements Helpful for Arthritis?, 4/4/19</p>

<p>Penn Medicine: 4 Head-To-Toe Ways That Collagen Can Improve Your Health, 11/4/18</p>

<p>Journal of Arthritis: Efficacy of Oral Collagen in Joint Pain - Osteoarthritis and Rheumatoid Arthritis, 2/28/17</p>

<p>Osteoarthritis and Cartilage: Efficacy of Specific Bioactive Collagen Peptides in the Treatment of Joint Pain, 4/26</p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew Robson</name></author><category term="Pain" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Benefits of Using Collagen For Your Joints]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The 3 Most Common Chiropractic Questions Answered</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/chiropractic/2019/the-3-most-common-chiropractic-questions-answered" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 3 Most Common Chiropractic Questions Answered" /><published>2019-11-14T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2023-07-19T11:22:46-03:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/chiropractic/2019/the-3-most-common-chiropractic-questions-answered</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/chiropractic/2019/the-3-most-common-chiropractic-questions-answered"><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-3-most-frequently-asked-chiropractic-care-questions-and-the-answers-to-them"><strong>The 3 Most Frequently Asked Chiropractic Care Questions and The Answers to Them</strong></h2>

<p>Most people have a few questions when considering chiropractic care to naturally treat pain and injuries. If you’ve been wondering if chiropractic is a good option for you, you’ll want to take a look at these commonly asked questions.</p>

<h2 id="1-what-kinds-of-conditions-do-chiropractors-treat"><strong>1. What Kinds of Conditions Do Chiropractors Treat?</strong></h2>

<p>Chiropractic treatment focuses on your muscles, vertebrae, joints, tendons, and ligaments. The treatment may be a good choice if you experience joint, muscle or nerve pain after a car accident, fall or another type of injury.</p>

<p>Accidents aren’t the only cause of pain. Fortunately, your chiropractor can also treat back, neck or shoulder pain related to poor posture, overuse injuries, tendonitis, bursitis, arthritis, and other conditions.</p>

<p>Pain and stiffness can occur when your spine becomes misaligned. Spinal misalignments cause your muscles and joints to become tight and stiff, and are responsible for pain and decreased range of motion. Misaligned vertebrae in your spine and tight muscles may also press on your nerves, triggering or increasing pain.</p>

<p>Chiropractic treatments are designed to improve the alignment of the spine, ease muscle tension and stiffness, relieve pressure on nerves, decrease inflammation, and improve range of motion and flexibility.</p>

<p><strong>Chiropractic treatment can helpful for many conditions, including:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Whiplash</li>
  <li>Headaches and Migraines</li>
  <li>Spinal Disc Issues</li>
  <li>Spinal Stenosis</li>
  <li>Osteoarthritis</li>
  <li>Pinched Nerves</li>
  <li>Dizziness</li>
  <li>Text Neck</li>
  <li>Leg Length Discrepancy</li>
  <li>Immune System Issues</li>
  <li>Temporomandibular Joint Dysfunction (TMJ)</li>
  <li>Tingling and Numbness in the Hands, Feet, Arms, and Legs</li>
  <li>Sciatica</li>
  <li>Scoliosis</li>
  <li>Pain in the Back, Neck, Head, Shoulders, Arms, Ribs, Hips, Legs, Feet and Pelvis</li>
  <li>Poor Posture</li>
  <li>Sprains and Strains</li>
  <li>Carpal Tunnel Syndrome</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="2-what-treatments-do-chiropractors-offer"><strong>2. What Treatments Do Chiropractors Offer?</strong></h2>

<p>If you’ve ever seen a character on a TV show or movie receive chiropractic care, you may assume that spinal manipulations are the only treatments chiropractors offer. During spinal manipulation, your chiropractor uses quick, hands-on pressure to realign the small vertebrae in your spinal column. Many people refer to this as “cracking the neck,” but the cracking sounds produced during manipulation are actually gas bubbles released from the joints.</p>

<h3 id="spinal-manipulation">Spinal Manipulation</h3>
<p>Improving the alignment of the spine with spinal manipulation reduces inflammation, improves flexibility and range of motion, enhances blood flow and decreases pressure on the joints, nerves, muscles, and ligaments.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In 2017, the Journal of the American Medical Association published a systematic review of studies that evaluated the effectiveness of spinal manipulation in treating acute low back pain. The review noted that manipulation was associated with less pain and improved function six weeks after treatment.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Other studies have shown spinal manipulation and chiropractic treatments to be effective in treating whiplash, neck pain, plantar fasciitis, hip and knee osteoarthritis, migraines and other conditions.</p>

<h3 id="flexion-distraction">Flexion Distraction</h3>
<p>Flexion-Distraction is also a technique we utilise at Droitwich Back and Neck Clinic. It is a technique designed to take pressure and strain away from bulging, inflamed discs of the spine. Using a very gentle stretching technique, we are able to create space in between vertebral discs helping to reduce pain and improve quality of movement. This technique is particularly useful for patients with sciatica and bulging discs.</p>

<h2 id="3-am-i-a-good-candidate-for-chiropractic-treatment"><strong>3. Am I a Good Candidate for Chiropractic Treatment?</strong></h2>

<p>Chiropractic care is a safe, effective treatment option for most people. During your first visit, your chiropractor will perform a thorough examination, order X-rays or other diagnostic tests, and discuss your medical history and symptoms before recommending a treatment plan.</p>

<p>Although medication can temporarily dull your pain, your symptoms will return unless you address the cause. Chiropractic treatment treats the source of your pain, eliminating or reducing the need for pain killers or other medications. It’s a good choice if you’re experiencing sudden or chronic pain or have other symptoms, such as:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Pain that affects any part of your body or shoots down your arms or legs</li>
  <li>Joint pain</li>
  <li>Muscle pain, weakness, tingling or numbness</li>
  <li>Difficulty walking, maintaining your balance, or sitting or standing without pain</li>
  <li>Frequent headaches, fatigue or difficulty concentrating due to your symptoms</li>
  <li>Chiropractic treatment can help relieve your symptoms naturally.</li>
</ul>

<p>Contact us if you’re ready to schedule an appointment today.</p>

<p><strong>Sources:</strong></p>

<p><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/28399251">Journal of the American Medical Association: Association of Spinal Manipulative Therapy with Clinical Benefit and Harm for Acute Low Back Pain, 4/11/17 </a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.spineuniverse.com/treatments/chiropractic/what-disorders-do-chiropractors-treat">Spine Universe: What Disorders Do Chiropractors Treat? </a></p>

<p><a href="https://health.usnews.com/health-news/patient-advice/articles/2015/11/30/surprise-chiropractors-can-treat-these-5-conditions">U.S. News &amp; World Report: Surprise: Chiropractors Can Treat These 5 Conditions, 11/30/15</a> </p>

<p><a href="https://www.acatoday.org/patients/why-choose-chiropractic/what-is-chiropractic">American Chiropractic Association: What is Chiropractic? </a></p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew Robson</name></author><category term="Chiropractic" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The 3 Most Frequently Asked Chiropractic Care Questions and The Answers to Them]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chiropractic and Headaches</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/headaches/2019/chiropractic-and-headaches" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chiropractic and Headaches" /><published>2019-11-14T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2023-07-19T11:22:46-03:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/headaches/2019/chiropractic-and-headaches</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/headaches/2019/chiropractic-and-headaches"><![CDATA[<h2 id="chiropractic-care-may-help-your-headache-pain"><strong>Chiropractic Care May Help Your Headache Pain</strong></h2>

<p>Headaches are often dismissed as minor ailments that can be easily cured simply by popping a few over-the-counter pain relievers. Although pain medication may be helpful for occasional headaches, it’s not always effective for chronic headache pain. Pain relievers can also cause liver or kidney damage and other serious side effects if you take too many of them. Fortunately, chiropractic care offers a drug-free treatment option.</p>

<h3 id="what-kind-of-headache-do-you-have"><strong>What Kind of Headache Do You Have?</strong></h3>

<p>Chiropractors often treat patients who have these types of headaches:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Tension Headaches:</strong> Tension headaches occur when the muscles in your neck and head contract and become too tight. You may feel tightness and pain in your forehead only, or the pain may wrap around to the back your head and your neck. The headaches can be caused by stress, poor posture, or even looking down at your cellphone for hours.</li>
  <li><strong>Migraine Headaches:</strong> Migraine, the sixth most disabling illness in the world, affects 18 percent of women, 6 percent of men and 10 percent of children in the U.S., according to the Migraine Research Foundation. Pain, nausea, vomiting, sensitivity to light and sound, in addition to other unpleasant symptoms, can affect the quality of your life and make it difficult to work or care for your family.</li>
  <li><strong>Cluster Headaches:</strong> These extremely painful headaches typically occur on one side of the head and last 10 minutes to several hours. They’re called “cluster” headaches because sufferers usually get multiple headaches in one day. The headaches can disappear for months at a time and may reappear at the same times every year.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>How Do Chiropractors Treat Headaches?</strong></p>

<p>Treatment options depend on the type of headache you have, but may include:</p>

<p><strong>Spinal Manipulation:</strong> Manipulation relieves pressure on your joints, realigns your spine, improves blood flow, and helps relax tight muscles. Your chiropractor uses his or her hands or an activator to apply quick, forceful pressure to the vertebrae. Spinal manipulation is particularly helpful if nerve irritation triggers your migraines or cluster headaches. Manipulation relieves pressure on your nerves, easing your pain and reducing the frequency of your headaches. <strong>Spinal Mobilization:</strong> Spinal mobilization involves gentle, hands-on pressure that stretches your spine, improves joint function, and helps ease tension in the muscles between the vertebrae. Since tense muscles can be an issue no matter what type of headache you experience, mobilization can be very effective. <strong>Massage:</strong> Massage is often included in treatment plans for headaches. The therapy loosens tight muscles, improves range of motion, increases blood flow, and may help reduce the frequency of your headaches. Regular massages also reduce stress, which can be a factor if you get tension headaches. <strong>Flexion-Distraction Therapy:</strong> This therapy is performed on a segmented table that moves or drops as your chiropractor gently manipulates your vertebrae. Flexion-distraction therapy reduces stiffness, improves range of motion in your back and neck, and may even help decrease the number of headaches you get every month. Your treatment plan might include a few other types of therapy, including ice and heat therapy, ultrasound treatment, or electrotherapy. Improving your posture and strengthening the muscles that support your head and neck may also be helpful. Your chiropractor can recommend exercises, make suggestions that will help you improve your posture, and provide advice about a healthy diet.</p>

<p><strong>Is Chiropractic Treatment Effective?</strong></p>

<p>In a case series published in Global Advances in Health and Medicine, researchers discussed the case of a 31-year-old patient whose migraines become chronic after two pregnancies. After chiropractic treatment, she experienced fewer migraines. During the 10th month, she reported no headaches during the entire month.</p>

<p>Another case study published in the Journal of Family Medicine and Primary Care examined the case of a 44-year old woman who suffered from daily headaches that didn’t respond to pain medication. During her treatment, spinal manipulation, ultrasound, and other therapies were used. After three months of treatment, her headache pain began to subside. The pain was completely eliminated by six months.</p>

<p>Are you tired of living with headache or migraine pain? We can help you control your symptoms naturally. Contact us to schedule an appointment.</p>

<p> </p>

<p><strong>Sources:</strong></p>

<p><a href="https://migraineresearchfoundation.org/about-migraine/migraine-facts/" target="_blank">Migraine Research Foundation: About Migraine </a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.acatoday.org/Patients/Health-Wellness-Information/Headaches-and-Chiropractic" target="_blank">American Chiropractic Association: Headaches and Chiropractic </a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6069670/" target="_blank">NCBI: Journal of Family Medicine and Primary Care: Long-Term Relief from Tension-Type Headache and Major Depression Following Chiropractic Treatment, May/June 2018</a> </p>

<p><a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/2164956119835778" target="_blank">Global Advances in Health and Medicine: Integrating Chiropractic Care into the Treatment of Migraine Headaches in a Tertiary Care Hospital: A Case Series, 3/28/19</a> </p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew Robson</name></author><category term="Headaches" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Chiropractic Care May Help Your Headache Pain]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Staying Healthy as a Caregiver</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/health/2019/staying-healthy-as-a-caregiver" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Staying Healthy as a Caregiver" /><published>2019-11-14T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2023-07-19T11:22:46-03:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/health/2019/staying-healthy-as-a-caregiver</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/health/2019/staying-healthy-as-a-caregiver"><![CDATA[<p><strong>How to Stay Healthy Mentally and Physically When You’re a Caregiver</strong></p>

<p>Taking care of others can be hard on your own health. In fact, 17 to 25 percent of caregivers say their health is fair or poor, according to the Family Caregiver Alliance. That statistic isn’t surprising. Whether you’re caring for young children or elderly relatives, caregiving is a demanding, stressful job. Following these tips will help you avoid injuries and health issues while also reducing stress in your life.</p>

<p><strong>Stay Active</strong></p>

<p>Lack of exercise is a common issue among caregivers. At the end of a long day, it can be hard to find the energy to work out. Yet, inactivity can increase your risk of developing a variety of health problems, including:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Obesity</li>
  <li>High Blood Pressure</li>
  <li>High Cholesterol</li>
  <li>Type 2 Diabetes</li>
  <li>Heart Disease</li>
  <li>Heart Attack</li>
  <li>Stroke</li>
  <li>Osteoporosis</li>
  <li>Depression</li>
  <li>Colon, Breast or Uterine Cancer</li>
</ul>

<p>Exercise offers a simple way to reduce your risk of developing these diseases and conditions. Even 10 or 15-minute exercise sessions can help you stay healthy. You don’t have to visit a gym or even leave the house to enjoy the benefits of exercise. Walking up and down the steps repeatedly, exercising to a video or jogging in place will get your blood flowing and help keep your heart, muscles, and bones strong.</p>

<p><strong>Don’t Neglect Your Interests</strong></p>

<p>You may have given up your favorite hobbies and leisure activities after you began caring for a friend or family member. Although your dedication is certainly commendable, you may soon feel depressed or stressed if your life only involves caregiving.</p>

<p>Find time to watch a favorite TV show, try the new restaurant in town or finish your woodworking project. If the person you care for requires 24-hour supervision, ask a friend to take over for you for a few hours or find out if home health agencies in your area offer respite care.</p>

<p><strong>Make Your Health a Priority</strong></p>

<p>You can’t take care of other people if you’re sick. Has your diet suffered since you became a caregiver? Eating a balanced diet is a crucial factor in good health. Make sure your meals include options from the major food groups and avoid carbohydrate-laden or sugary snacks.</p>

<p>Make (and keep) appointments with your doctor when you don’t feel well. The longer you put off receiving medical care, the worse your illness or condition can become. Visiting your doctor promptly will help you ensure that you’re well enough to care for your family member or friend.</p>

<p><strong>Use Safe Lifting Techniques</strong></p>

<p>Poor lifting techniques can cause injuries that make it difficult or impossible to care for your relative. According to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, over 17 percent of caregivers reported that they experienced 14 or more physically unhealthy days over a month’s time span.</p>

<p>Lifting with your legs while keeping your neck and head aligned can help you avoid injury, as can using a lifting belt to help transfer a person from a wheelchair or bed. No matter how cautiously you move, injuries can still happen. Don’t be reluctant to ask for help if you don’t think you can move the person safely.</p>

<p><strong>See Your Chiropractor</strong></p>

<p>It’s not unusual for caregivers to develop stiffness and pain, particularly in their necks and backs. Ignoring your symptoms may worsen pain and decrease your range of motion.</p>

<p>Regular visits to your chiropractor help you reduce pain and other symptoms. Using spinal manipulation, soft tissue mobilization, massage, and other techniques, your chiropractor can realign your spine, decrease muscle stiffness and pain, and speed healing of injured areas by increasing blood flow.</p>

<p>Both you and your family member or friend benefit when you take care of yourself. If caregiving is taking a toll on your body, we can help. Contact us to schedule your chiropractic appointment.</p>

<p><strong>Sources:</strong></p>

<p><a href="https://www.heart.org/en/health-topics/caregiver-support/top-10-caregiver-tips-for-staying-healthy-and-active" target="_blank">American Heart Association: Top 10 Caregiver Tips for Staying Healthy and Active, 6/30/17</a> </p>

<p><a href="https://www.cdc.gov/aging/caregiving/caregiver-brief.html" target="_blank">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention: Caregiving for Family and Friends - A Public Health Issue</a> </p>

<p><a href="https://www.caregiver.org/pilotIntegration/indexPersistent.html?uri=%2Fcaregiver-statistics-health-technology-and-caregiving-resources" target="_blank">Family Caregiver Alliance: Caregiver Statistics: Health, Technology and Caregiving Resources</a> </p>

<p><a href="https://medlineplus.gov/healthrisksofaninactivelifestyle.html" target="_blank">Medline Plus: Health Risks of an Inactive Lifestyle </a></p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew Robson</name></author><category term="Health" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How to Stay Healthy Mentally and Physically When You’re a Caregiver]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Make Sure Your Chiropractic Adjustment Lasts</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/adjustments/2019/how-to-make-sure-your-chiropractic-adjustment-lasts" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Make Sure Your Chiropractic Adjustment Lasts" /><published>2019-11-14T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2023-07-19T12:40:25-03:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/adjustments/2019/how-to-make-sure-your-chiropractic-adjustment-lasts</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/adjustments/2019/how-to-make-sure-your-chiropractic-adjustment-lasts"><![CDATA[<h2 id="how-to-extend-the-effects-of-your-chiropractic-adjustment"><strong>How to Extend the Effects of Your Chiropractic Adjustment</strong></h2>

<p>Depending on the things you do after your visit to the chiropractor, the effects of your treatment can last days or just a few hours. Fortunately, you can extend the positive effects of your adjustments by following a few simple guidelines.</p>

<h3 id="pay-attention-to-your-posture"><strong>Pay Attention to Your Posture</strong></h3>

<p>Poor posture can contribute to spinal misalignments, tight muscles and other uncomfortable symptoms. Although you may feel better after the adjustment, your results won’t last very long if you slouch or spend hours hunched over your laptop or phone. When you use your phone or another digital device, hold it at eye level if possible. Constantly looking down at devices puts enormous strain on your neck and may even cause permanent damage to your spine if you don’t change your habits.</p>

<h3 id="use-ergonomic-furniture"><strong>Use Ergonomic Furniture</strong></h3>

<p>Slouching may be unavoidable if your chair and desk force your body into an uncomfortable position. Ergonomic chairs keep your spine properly aligned, support your lower back, and distribute your weight evenly. When they’re combined with ergonomic desks and keyboards, you may be much less likely to experience aches and pains at the end of the day.</p>

<p>Standing desks offer another ergonomic option. Using a standing desk several times throughout the day can reduce pain in your upper back and neck and may improve your productivity. The desks are adjustable and move up and down to allow you to move easily from a seated to a standing position.</p>

<h3 id="take-regular-breaks"><strong>Take Regular Breaks</strong></h3>

<p>Improving your posture and using ergonomic furniture can help you keep your spine properly aligned, but pain may still be a problem if you spend long hours at your desk. Add frequent breaks to your daily schedule to prevent pain and discomfort. Take a short walk (even if it’s only to the end of the hall) and do a few stretches before you return to your desk.</p>

<h3 id="avoid-awkward-movements-or-lifting"><strong>Avoid Awkward Movements or Lifting</strong></h3>

<p>Activities that involve awkward movements or require you to contort your body can cause aches and pains. Painting the ceiling or digging new posts for your fence the day after your treatment can reverse the results of your adjustment.</p>

<p>Poor lifting techniques can also ruin the effects of chiropractic adjustments. Don’t be afraid to ask for help and use your knees and legs, rather than your back, when you lift.</p>

<h3 id="fill-your-water-bottle"><strong>Fill Your Water Bottle</strong></h3>

<p>Water helps your body get rid of toxins that are released after an adjustment. Increasing your water intake for a few days after your treatment can be very beneficial. Water improves joint lubrication, which may help keep your joints become more flexible. Upping your water intake can also help you avoid dehydration, a condition that can cause headaches, muscle weakness, dizziness, fatigue, and irritability.</p>

<h3 id="get-a-little-exercise"><strong>Get a Little Exercise</strong></h3>

<p>Although you won’t want to participate in strenuous activities soon after an adjustment, low-impact exercise will help keep your muscles loose and improve your range of motion. Walking, swimming, biking, yoga, Pilates and other forms of exercise will enhance your adjustment results.</p>

<p>Your chiropractor may have taught you a few exercises you can do at home to improve the strength and flexibility of your muscles. These exercises are an important part of your treatment plan and should be performed as often as your chiropractor recommends.</p>

<h3 id="dont-skimp-on-sleep"><strong>Don’t Skimp on Sleep</strong></h3>

<p>Sleep plays a pivotal role in the healing process. While you’re sleeping, your body repairs muscles and tissues and produces hormones that reduce inflammation. If you don’t get seven to eight hours of sleep every night, you may be unwittingly sabotaging the effects of your chiropractic treatment.</p>

<p>Do you sleep on your back? This position may be a factor in your pain. The American Chiropractic Association notes that you put approximately 50 pounds of pressure on your back when you sleep on it.</p>

<p>Chiropractic adjustments offer a simple, natural way to control pain in your joints and muscles. Contact us if you’re ready to schedule an appointment.</p>

<h4 id="sources"><strong>Sources:</strong></h4>

<p><a href="https://ceoworld.biz/2019/03/18/7-benefits-of-ergonomic-office-chair-you-shouldnt-miss/" target="_blank">CEO World Magazine: 7 Benefits of Ergonomic Office Chairs You Shouldn’t Miss</a> </p>

<p><a href="https://www.acatoday.org/Patients/Health-Wellness-Information/Spinal-Health" target="_blank">American Chiropractic Association: Tips for a Healthy Spine </a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.spine-health.com/treatment/chiropractic/exercise-and-chiropractic-therapy" target="_blank">Spine-Health: Exercise and Chiropractic Therapy</a> </p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew Robson</name></author><category term="Adjustments" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How to Extend the Effects of Your Chiropractic Adjustment]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Risk Of Fall For Senior Citizens</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/seniors/2018/risk-falling-senior-citizens" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Risk Of Fall For Senior Citizens" /><published>2018-08-08T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2023-07-19T11:22:46-03:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/seniors/2018/risk-falling-senior-citizens</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/seniors/2018/risk-falling-senior-citizens"><![CDATA[<p>Chiropractic is shown to reduce the risk of fall for senior citizens. Watch the video for more information.</p>

<iframe width="100%" height="500" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Cs9FHh4uSDQ" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>]]></content><author><name>Andrew Robson</name></author><category term="Seniors" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Chiropractic is shown to reduce the risk of fall for senior citizens. Watch the video for more information.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chiropractic Approach Versus Alternatives</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/chiropractic/2018/chiropractic-versus-alternatives" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chiropractic Approach Versus Alternatives" /><published>2018-08-06T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2023-07-19T11:22:46-03:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/chiropractic/2018/chiropractic-versus-alternatives</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/blog/chiropractic/2018/chiropractic-versus-alternatives"><![CDATA[<p>Chiropractic care results in superior improvements to quality of life in comparison with the alternatives. Watch the video for more information.</p>

<iframe width="100%" height="500" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/HlgTb45HAO8" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>]]></content><author><name>Andrew Robson</name></author><category term="Chiropractic" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Chiropractic care results in superior improvements to quality of life in comparison with the alternatives. Watch the video for more information.]]></summary></entry></feed>